Well, I was introduced as
لقد تمّ تقديمي على
the former Governor of Michigan,
أنّني الحاكمة السابقة لميتشقن،
but actually I'm a scientist.
لكن في الحقيقة أنا عالمة.
All right, a political scientist, it doesn't really count,
حسنًا، عالمة دبلوماسية. هذا لا يحتسب فعلا،
but my laboratory was the laboratory of democracy
لكن مختبري كان مختبرا للديموقراطية
that is Michigan, and, like any good scientist,
في ميتشقن، ومثل أي عالم جيد،
I was experimenting with policy
كنت أختبر السياسة
about what would achieve the greatest good
عمّا يمكن أن يحقق الأشياء الجيدة
for the greatest number.
لأكبر عدد.
But there were three problems, three enigmas
لكن كانت هناك ثلاث مشكلات، ثلاث ألغاز
that I could not solve,
لم أكن قادرة على حلّها
and I want to share with you those problems,
وأريد أن أشارك معكم هذه المشاكل،
but most importantly,
لكن الأكثر أهمية هو
I think I figured out a proposal for a solution.
أظن أنني وجدت اقتراحًا للحل.
The first problem
المشكلة الأولى
that not just Michigan, but every state, faces is,
التي تواجهها ليس فقط ميتشقن بل كل الولايات
how do you create good jobs in America
هي كيفية إيجاد فرص وظيفية في أمريكا
in a global economy?
في ظل اقتصاد عالمي؟
So let me share with you some empirical data from my lab.
إذن دعوني الآن أشارككم بعض البيانات التجريبية التي تحصلت عليها من معملي.
I was elected in 2002 and, at the end of my first year in office in 2003,
لقد تمّ انتخابي في عام 2002، في نهاية سنتي الأولى في المكتب عام 2003،
I got a call from one of my staff members, who said,
وصلتني مكالمة من أحد أعضاء فريقي، والذي قال:
"Gov, we have a big problem.
"سيدتي، لدينا مشكلة كبيرة.
We have a little tiny community called Greenville, Michigan,
لدينا مجتمع صغير للغاية يسمى "غرينفيل، ميشيغان"
population 8,000,
عدد سكانه 8000
and they are about to lose their major employer,
وهم على وشك أن يخسروا مُشغّلهم الرئيسي
which is a refrigerator factory that's operated by Electrolux."
والذي هو مصنع تبريد تديره إلكترولوكس."
And I said, "Well, how many people work at Electrolux?"
فقلت له: حسنًا، كم عدد الأشخاص الذين يعملون في إلكترولوكس؟"
And he said, "3,000 of the 8,000 people in Greenville."
فقال: "3000 شخص من أصل 8000 في غرينفيل."
So it is a one-company town.
إذن هي مدينة تعتمد على شركة واحدة.
And Electrolux was going to go to Mexico.
وإلكترولوكس كانت ذاهبة للانتقال إلى المكسيك.
So I said, "Forget that. I'm the new Governor.
لذلك قلت له:"انسَ ذلك. أنا سأكون الحاكم الجديد.
We can fix this. We're going to go to Greenville
نستطيع إصلاح هذا. سنذهب إلى غرينفيل
with my whole cabinet and we will just
مع مجلسي الاستشاري وسوف
make Electrolux an offer they can't refuse."
نقدّم لإلكترولوكس عرضًا لن تتمكن من رفضه."
So I brought my whole cabinet,
أحضرت جميع أفراد مجلسي الاستشاري،
and we met with all of the pooh-bahs of little Greenville --
واجتمعنا مع كبار الشخصيات في غرينفيل:
the mayor, the city manager, the head of the community college --
الرئيس، مدير المدينة، رئيس كلية المجتمع.
and we basically emptied our pockets
بشكل أساسي، أفرغنا جيوبنا
and put all of our chips on the table,
ووضعنا كل ما لدينا على الطاولة.
incentives, you name it, to convince Electrolux to stay,
كل أنواع الحوافز -عددها بنفسك!- لإقناع إلكترولوكس بالبقاء.
and as we made our pile of chips,
وعندما تشكّلت كومة،
we slid them across the table to the management of Electrolux.
مرّرناها عبر الطاولة إلى مدير إلكترولوكس.
And in the pile were things like zero taxes for 20 years,
الحوافز كانت أشياء مثل: عدم دفع ضرائب لمدة 20 سنة،
or that we'd help to build a new factory for the company,
أو المساعدة في بناء مصنع جديد للشركة،
we'd help to finance it. The UAW, who represented the workers,
أو المساعدة في تمويل الشركة. تحالف العمال في المصانع
said they would offer unprecedented concessions,
قالوا أنّهم سيقدّمون تنازلات لا مثيل لها،
sacrifices to just keep those jobs in Greenville.
تضحيات من أجل المحافظة على الوظائف في غرينفيل.
So the management of Electrolux took our pile,
قامت إدارة إلكترولوكس بأخذ الكومة،
our list of incentives, and they went outside the room
والتي هي قائمتنا بالحوافز المقدمة، وخرجوا من الغرفة
for 17 minutes,
لمدة 17 دقيقة،
and they came back in and they said,
ثم عادوا وقالوا:
"Wow, this is the most generous
"وااااو، هذا أسخى عرض
any community has ever been to try to keep jobs here.
قُدّم من أجل المحافظة على الوظائف هنا.
But there's nothing you can do
لكن لا يوجد شيء تستطيعون تقديمه
to compensate for the fact that we can pay $1.57 an hour
لتعويض حقيقة أنّنا نستطيع أن ندفع 1.57 دولار لساعة العمل الواحدة
in Juarez, Mexico. So we're leaving."
في خواريز، المكسيك. لذا نحن سنغادر إلى هناك."
And they did. And when they did, it was like
وقد فعلوا. وعندما فعلوا ذلك، كان الوضع مثل
a nuclear bomb went off in little Greenville.
قنبلة نووية تفجرت في غرينفيل.
In fact, they did implode the factory.
في الحقيقة، لقد دمّروا المصنع.
That's a guy that is walking on his last day of work.
هذا شخص يمشي في يوم عمله الأخير.
And on the month that the last refrigerator rolled off the assembly line,
وفي الشهر الذي ظهرت فيه آخر ثلاجة من خط التجميع،
the employees of Electrolux in Greenville, Michigan,
اجتمع موظّفو الكترولكس في غرينفل، ميشغن،
had a gathering for themselves that they called the last supper.
وسمّوا ذلك الإجتماع العشاء الأخير.
It was in a big pavilion in Greenville, an indoor pavilion,
لقد كان جناحًا كبيرًا في غرينفيل، جناح داخلي.
and I went to it because I was so frustrated as Governor
ولقد ذهبت إليه لأنني كنت محبطة جدًا لأنني الحاكمة
that I couldn't stop the outflow of these jobs,
التي لم تستطع إيقاف فقدان تلك الوظائف.
and I wanted to grieve with them,
أردت أن أشاركهم الحزن.
and as I went into the room-- there's thousands of people there.
عندما دخلت الغرفة، كان هناك آلاف الأشخاص.
It was a just big thing. People were eating boxed lunches
لقد كان شيئًا كبيرًا. الأشخاص كانوا يأكلون غداءً معلّبًا
on roundtop tables, and there was a sad band playing music,
على طاولة مستديرة، وكان هناك فرقة حزينة تعزف الموسيقى،
or a band playing sad music, probably both. (Laughter)
أو فرقة تعزف موسيقى حزينة، كلاهما على الأغلب! (ضحك)
And this guy comes up to me,
ثم قام أحد الأشخاص بالمجيء إليّ،
and he's got tattoos and his ponytail and his baseball cap on,
موشوم الجسم، وشعره على هيئة ذيل حصان، يرتدي قبعة بيسبول.
and he had his two daughters with him,
وكان معه طفلتاه.
and he said, "Gov, these are my two daughters."
قال:"سيدتي، هاتان الاثنتان طفلتيّ."
He said, "I'm 48 years old,
قال:"أنا في الثامنة والأربعين من عمري،
and I have worked at this factory for 30 years.
وقد اشتغلت في هذا المصنع لمدة ثلاثين سنة.
I went from high school to factory.
لقد ذهبت من الثانوية العامة إلى المصنع مباشرة.
My father worked at this factory," he said.
أبي عمل في هذا المصنع.
"My grandfather worked at this factory.
جدّي عمل في هذا المصنع.
All I know is how to make refrigerators."
وكل ما أعرفه هو كيف أصنع برّادات."
And he looked at his daughters,
نظر إلى طفلتيه،
and he puts his hand on his chest,
ثم وضع يده على صدره،
and he says, "So, Gov, tell me,
وقال:"إذن قولي لي،
who is ever going to hire me?
من سيقوم بتوظيفي بعد الآن؟
Who is ever going to hire me?"
من سيقوم بتوظيفي بعد الآن؟"
And that was asked not just by that guy
وهذا السؤال لم يكن موجهًا من ذلك الشخص فقط
but by everyone in the pavilion,
بل من كل شخص في الجناح.
and frankly, by every worker at one of the 50,000 factories
وبصراحة، بل هو موجّه من كل عامل في 50,000 مصنع
that closed in the first decade of this century.
أغلقت في بداية العقد الأول من هذا القرن.
Enigma number one: How do you create jobs
المعضلة الأولى: كيف توفّر وظائف عمل
in America in a global economy?
في أمريكا تحت ظل اقتصاد عالمي؟
Number two, very quickly:
المعضلة الثانية بشكل سريع:
How do you solve global climate change
كيف تحلّ تغيرات المناخ العالمي
when we don't even have a national energy policy in this country
في وقت نحن لا نملك فيه سياسة فعالة عالمية في هذه البلاد
and when gridlock in Congress seems to be the norm?
وفي وقت يكون الجمود في الكونغرس يبدو شيئًا طبيعيًا؟
In fact, there was a poll that was done recently
في الحقيقة، هناك استفتاء تمّ مؤخرًا
and the pollster compared Congress's approval ratings
حيث قارن منظم الإستفتآت معدل استحسان الكونغرس
to a number of other unpleasant things,
مع الأشياء الكريهة،
and it was found, in fact, that Congress's approval rating
وقد وجد، في الحقيقة، أن معدّل استحسان الكونغرس
is worse than cockroaches,
هو أسواء من الصراصير،
lice, Nickelback the band, root canals and Donald Trump. (Laughter)
القمل، فرقة نيكلباك، سحب عصب الأسنان و دونالد ترمب. (ضحك)
But wait, the good news is it's at least better
لكن انتظر، الأخبار الجيدة أن الكونغرس على الأقل أفضل من
than meth labs and gonorrhea. (Laughter)
مختبر الميثامفيتامين و السيلان. (ضحك)
We got a problem, folks.
لدينا مشكلة، أيها السادة.
So it got me thinking, what is it?
إنها تجعلني أفكر، ماهي؟
What in the laboratory that I see out there,
ماذا يحدث للمختبر الذي أراه هناك،
the laboratories of democracy, what has happened?
مختبر الديمقراطية، ماذا حدث؟
What policy prescriptions have happened
ماهي وصفة السياسة التي حدثت
that actually cause changes to occur
والتي أدت لحدوث هذه التغيرات
and that have been accepted in a bipartisan way?
والتي تم الموافقة عليه من الحزبين؟
So if I asked you, for example,
إذا سألتكم، مثلا،
what was the Obama Administration policy
ماهي سياسة ادارة اوباما
that caused massive changes across the country,
والتي أحدثت تغيير كبيرا عبر البلاد،
what would you say?
ماذا ستقولون؟
You might say Obamacare, except for those were not voluntary changes.
قد تقولوا خطة أوباما لتأمين الرعاية الصحية للجميع، فيما عدا أولئك الذين لم يرغبوا بالتغيير الطوعي.
As we know, only half the states have opted in.
كما نعرف، نصف الولايات فقط اختارت التحول.
We might say the Recovery Act, but those didn't require policy changes.
قد نقول خطة التعافي، لكن هؤولاء لا يطلبون تغيير السياسة.
The thing that caused massive policy changes to occur
ما أدى إلى تغيير السياسة
was Race to the Top for education.
هو السباق إلى قمة التعليم.
Why? The government put a $4.5 billion pot
لماذا؟ الحكومة وضعت 4.5 مليار دولار
and said to the governors across the country, compete for it.
وقالت للحكام عبر البلاد، تنافسوا عليها.
Forty-eight governors competed,
ثمانية وأربعين حاكما تنافسوا،
convincing 48 state legislatures to essentially
مقنعين 48 مشرعا ولاية لكي
raise standards for high schoolers
يرفعوا من جودة التعليم لطلاب المدارس العليا
so that they all take a college prep curriculum.
بحيث يدرس جميعهم منهاج التحضير لدخول الكلية.
Forty-eight states opted in, creating a national [education] policy from the bottom up.
شارك 48 ولاية في هذا، وأوجدوا سياسة تعليم وطنية جديدة.
So I thought, well, why can't we do something like that
هذا دفعني للتفكير، حسنا، لماذا لا نقوم بعمل شيء مماثل
and create a clean energy jobs race to the top?
ونوجد سباقا لوظائف الطاقة النظيفة ؟
Because after all, if you look at the context,
لأنه في النهاية، إذا نظرت إلى السياق،
1.6 trillion dollars has been invested in the past eight years
1.6 تريليون دولار قد استثمرت في السنوات الثمانية
from the private sector globally,
من القطاع الخاص عبر العالم،
and every dollar represents a job,
وكل دولار يمثل عملا،
and where are those jobs going?
لكن أين تذهب هذه الوظائف؟
Well, they're going to places that have policy, like China.
حسنا، إنها تذهب إلى أماكن لديها سياسة، مثل الصين.
In fact, I was in China to see what they were doing,
في الحقيقة، ذهبت للصين لأرى ماذا يفعلون،
and they were putting on a dog-and-pony show for the group that I was with,
وكان يضعون عرضا مبالغا فيه للمجموعة التي كنت فيها،
and I was standing in the back of the room during one of the demonstrations
وكنت أقف في آخر الغرفة في أثناء أحد التوضيحات
and standing next to one of the Chinese officials,
بجانب أحد المسؤولين الصينين،
and we were watching, and he says,
وأثناء مشاهدتنا، قال،
"So, Gov, when do you think the U.S. is going to get national energy policy?"
"أيتها الحاكمة، متى تتوقّعين أن تقوم الولايات المتحدة باعتماد سياسة وطنية للطاقة؟"
And I said, "Oh my God -- Congress, gridlock, who knows?"
وقلت له، "يا الاهي -- الكونغرس، عقبة، من يعرف متى؟"
And this is what he did, he goes, he says,
وهذا مافعله، ذهب، وقال،
"Take your time."
"خذوا وقتكم."
Because they see our passivity as their opportunity.
لأنهم يرون في سلبيتنا فرصة لهم.
So what if we decided to create
ماذا لو قررنا أن نوجد
a challenge to the governors of the country,
تحديا لحكام البلاد،
and the price to entry into this competition
وثمن الدخول لهذا التحدي
used the same amount that the bipartisan group approved in Congress
يستخدم نفس المبالغ التي وافق عليها مجموعة الحزبين في الكونغرس
for the Race to the Top for education, 4.5 billion,
لسباق القمة في التعليم، 4.5 مليار،
which sounds like a lot, but actually it's less than
والتي تبدوا كثير، لكنها أقل
one tenth of one percent of federal spending.
من واحد على عشرة من واحد بالمئة من المصاريف الفيدرالية.
It's a rounding error on the federal side.
إنّها كخطأ في التقريب من الطرف الفيدرالي.
But price to entry into that competition would be,
لكن السعر للدخول في هذه المنافسة سيكون،
you could just, say, use the President's goal.
يمكنك فقط، القول، استخدم هدف الرئيس.
He wants Congress to adopt a clean energy standard
إنه يريد من الكنغرس أن يتبنى مقاييس الطاقة النظيفة
of 80 percent by 2030,
بـ 80 بالمئة بحلول 2030،
in other words, that you'd have to get 80 percent
بالأحرى، عليكم الحصول على 80 بالمئة
of your energy from clean sources by the year 2030.
من طاقتكم من مصادر الطاقة النظيفة بحلول سنة 2030.
Why not ask all of the states to do that instead?
بدلا من ذلك، لماذا لا تطلب من جميع الولايات عمل ذلك ؟
And imagine what might happen,
وتصور مايمكن أن يحدث،
because every region has something to offer.
لأن كل منطقة لديها شيء تقدمه.
You might take states like Iowa and Ohio --
خذ ولاية مثل أيوا و أوهايو --
two very important political states, by the way --
ولايتين مهمتين جدا سياسيا، بالمناسبة --
those two governors, and they would say,
هؤولاء الحاكمين، وسيقولون،
we're going to lead the nation in producing
سنقوم بقيادة البلاد بانتاج
the wind turbines and the wind energy.
توربينات الرياح وطاقة الرياح.
You might say the solar states, the sun belt,
يمكن أن تقول الولايات الشمسية، حزام الشمس،
we're going to be the states that produce solar energy for the country,
سنكون الولايات التي تنتج الطاقة الشمسية للبلاد،
and maybe Jerry Brown says, "Well, I'm going to create
وربما يقول جيري براون، "حسنا سأقوم بايجاد
an industry cluster in California
كتلة صناعية في كاليفورنيا
to be able to produce the solar panels
لنتمكن من انتاج الواح الطاقة الشمسية
so that we're not buying them from China
لكي لا نشتريهم من الصين
but we're buying them from the U.S."
بل من الولايات المتحدة."
In fact, every region of the country could do this.
في الحقيقة، كل منطقة في البلاد تستطيع فعل ذلك.
You see, you've got solar and wind opportunity all across the nation.
تأمل، لديك فرص للطاقة الشمسية وطاقة الرياح في كل أرجاء البلاد.
In fact, if you look just at the upper and northern states
في الحقيقة، إذا نظرت فقط إلى المناطق العليا والولايات الشمالية
in the West, they could do geothermal,
في الغرب، يستطيعون الإستفادة من طاقة الأرض الباطنية،
or you could look at Texas and say,
أو تستطيع النظر إلى تكساس والقول،
we could lead the nation in the solutions to smart grid.
يمكننا قيادة البلاد لحلول خطوط الكهرباء النظيفة.
In the middle eastern states which have access to forests
في ولايات الشرق الأوسط والتي تستطيع الوصول للغابات
and to agricultural waste, they might say,
ولمخلفات الزراعة، يمكن أن يقولوا،
we're going to lead the nation in biofuels.
سنقود البلاد في مجال الوقود الحيوي.
In the upper northeast, we're going to lead the nation
في الجزء الشمالي الشرقي العلوي، سنقوم بقيادة البلاد
in energy efficiency solutions.
بحلول فعالية الطاقة.
Along the eastern seaboard, we're going to lead the nation
على طول ساحل البحر الشرقي، سنقوم بقيادة البلاد
in offshore wind.
بطاقة الرياح في داخل البحار.
You might look at Michigan and say, we're going to lead the nation
يمكنك النظر إلى ميشيغن والقول، سنقود البلاد
in producing the guts for the electric vehicle, like the lithium ion battery.
بانتاج قطع السيارات الكهربائية، مثل بطاريات الليثوم أيون.
Every region has something to offer,
كل منطقة لديها شيء لتقدّمه،
and if you created a competition,
وإذا خلقت المنافسة،
it respects the states and it respects federalism.
التي تحترم الولايات و الفيدرالية.
It's opt-in. You might even get Texas and South Carolina,
ربما تدخل تكساس وساوث كارولاينا،
who didn't opt into the education Race to the Top,
واللتان امتنعتا عن الدخول في السباق نحو القمة في التعليم،
you might even get them to opt in. Why?
ربما تجعلهم يفضلون الدخول لماذا؟
Because Republican and Democratic governors
لأن الحكام الديمقراطيين والجمهوريين
love to cut ribbons.
يحبون قطع الأشرطة.
We want to bring jobs. I'm just saying.
نريد أن ننشأ فرصا وظيفية. أنا فقط أقول ذلك.
And it fosters innovation at the state level
وهذا يعزز الإبداع على مستوى الولاية
in these laboratories of democracy.
في مختبرات الديمقراطية.
Now, any of you who are watching anything about politics lately
الآن، ربما يقول أحدكم، والذي يشاهد أي شيء عن السياسة مؤخرا
might say, "Okay, great idea, but really?
"حسنا إنها فكرة جيدة لكن حقا؟
Congress putting four and a half billion dollars on the table?
الكنغرس يضع أربعة مليارات دولار على الطاولة؟
They can't agree to anything."
لا يمكنهم الموافقة على أي شيء."
So you could wait and go through Congress,
لذلك يمكنك الإنتظار والذهاب عبر الكونغرس،
although you should be very impatient.
بالرغم من أنه يجب أن تكون عديم الصبر.
Or, you renegades, we could go around Congress.
أو، أن تتنكّر للمباديء السياسية، نستطيع أن نهمّش الكونغرس.
Go around Congress.
نتجاوز الكونغرس.
What if we created a private sector challenge to the governors?
ماذا لو أوجدنا تحديا في القطاع الخاص للحكام؟
What if several of the high-net worth companies
ماذا لو قرّرت مجموعة من الشركات ذات القيمة العالية
and individuals who are here at TED decided
والأفراد مثل الحاضرين هنا في TED
that they would create, band together, just a couple of them,
أن يوجدوا، ويتحدوا سوية، فقط مجموعة منهم،
and create a national competition to the governors
ويوجدوا منافسة وطنية للحكام
to have a race to the top
ليتسابقوا نحو القمة
and see how the governors respond?
وينظروا ردّ الحكام؟
What if it all started here at TED?
ماذا لو بدأت كلها هنا في TED؟
What if you were here
ماذا لوكنتم هنا
when we figured out how to crack the code
عندما وجدنا الحل لكيفية فك التشفير
to create good paying jobs in America -- (Applause) --
لإيجاد وظائف ذات مردود مادي جيد في أمريكا -- (تصفيق) --
and get national energy policy
وعمل سياسة وطنية للطاقة
and we created a national energy strategy from the bottom up?
ومن ثم عمل استراتيجية متكاملة للطاقة ؟
Because, dear TEDsters,
لأنه ، أعزائي محبّي TED،
if you are impatient like I am,
إذا كنتم غير صبوريين مثلي،
you know that our economic competitors,
تعرفون أن منافيسينا الاقتصاديين،
our other nations, are in the game
والأمم الأخرى، هم في اللعبة
and are eating us for lunch.
وهم يأكلوننا على الغداء.
And we can get in the game or not.
ونستطيع الدخول في اللعبة أو لا.
We can be at the table or we can be on the table.
يمكننا أن نشارك في الأكل أو أن نكون طبقا على الطاولة.
And I don't know about you,
وأنا لا أعرف ما ترغبونه،
but I prefer to dine.
لكني أفضل المشاركة في الطعام.
Thank you all so much. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلًا لكم جميعًا. (تصفيق)